Okay, it's high noon in Old Cheyenne.
Welcome to the Cinco de Mayo, the snowy
Cinco de Mayo uh meeting of the finance
committee. Call us to order. Uh
making a public comment.
We would like to have your address and
your name. And also
make sure if you're in the room, you
have your cell phones turned to silent
or vibrate or off. And with that, I'll
have the clerk read the first item.
Number 14, ordinance second reading,
amending enforcement and permitting
requirements related to oversized
vehicles and making conforming
amendments.
>> This
staff report,
>> Mr. Chairman, David Hopinson, deputy
city attorney.
The proposed ordinance before you
primarily makes three changes uh to the
oversized vehicles section.
It uh as currently existing in city
code, there are kind of two components
or enforcement mechanisms, one with
compliance and one with CPD.
Uh this ordinance would change that and
make enforcement of the oversized
vehicles exclusively in CPD's province.
So it take removes it from
the compliance department removes it as
a nuisance in the city code.
It changes the definition of oversized
vehicle
on page six
and just adds some language in there for
some clarification.
And the second sentence of that
subsection seven provides that any
actual measurements shall be increased
as necessary to account for deflated
tires or missing tires uh or similar
conditions rendering the vehicle
inoperable or limiting or reducing
operability. Uh this was an effort to
account for uh oversized vehicles that
maybe don't have their tires and then
fall under the size limitations um so
that law enforcement would be able to
account for that and properly sight a
vehicle.
And then finally,
it limits the permits that are available
uh to have your oversized vehicle on the
street. Um on page nine
in section F there, it would limit that
to not more than two permits uh would be
a issued within any 30-day period for
the same vehicle. And this is to address
concerns that
uh people are able to purchase
consecutive permits and effectively have
their oversized vehicle on the street
indefinitely.
Um,
the rest of the changes that you see in
there are primarily conforming
amendments. And with that, I'd be happy
to answer any questions about the
ordinance.
>> Any comments or questions from the
committee? Councilman Moody.
>> Yep.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. Three. Uh, thank
you, sir. On page five
in boards deleting B in addition to
vehicle uh nuisance provisions and then
one, two, three, and C. Does that mean
that people won't be able to park
between Memorial Day and Labor Day
anymore?
>> No. So, uh,
through you, uh, Councilman Moody, that
language is repeated in the in title 10
or in the CPD's enforcement. This is
just removing it from the nuisance
provisions of the code. So, that
language still exists. Um, and you
actually see it.
I'm not sure if it's
in here because I don't know that we
made any changes to it,
but Mr. Hopkins and it's on page nine of
section D. There we go.
I missed that. Thank you.
>> Any other questions from the committee?
You go to public comment in the room.
>> Welcome, Dr. Aldrich.
>> Good morning. Good afternoon. Uh Dr.
Michelle Aldrich, uh W three city
council representative.
Um I just wanted to uh speak to this. Um
this is a result of many uh phone calls
and emails. um from a variety of sources
um that have been concerned about um a
variety of things. One being that um
historically this ordinance has been
complaint driven, meaning enforcement of
it, meaning that um someone actually had
to place a complaint um about a neighbor
or an individual before um any action
was taken. and um that resulted in a lot
of referrals to the um community service
officers, the CSOS.
We also um in talking with Chief
Francisco within the first month or so
of this ordinance going into place, we
had an individual who went in and got 15
permits at one time. Um because it's
cheaper to get 15 permits um and at $75
for those 15 permits than it is to pay
for um parking his oversized vehicle in
a um commercial entity or lot or taking
it off the street. So, um there were and
we also the third um issue was we have a
a camper that even as we speak today is
sitting on College Drive and um when
an individual from the police department
and I went out and measured that
together. Um it is if the tires are
inflated, it's um just over 9 foot. If
the tires are not inflated, it's under 9
foot. Yeah, it's a a good time. Uh
mostly the tires are under inflated um
because it has flat tires. Um we have
been working with this trying to get it
removed or dealt with for about a year
and a half. Um it finally within the
last uh 3 weeks has been green tagged um
so that hopefully we can get off of
college drive. Um but we've just have
seen some um
areas that we really needed to tweak. I
know the question came up as to why
right now and um part of that is that we
are getting ready to go into the period
of time which is 5 days but before
Memorial Day till 5 days after Labor Day
when these oversized vehicles are um
allowed to be um on the streets. Um but
with that in mind, we wanted to make
sure that people knew what the um
guidelines would be coming back um after
Labor Day and before they're purchasing
these um oversized vehicles for
recreational purposes. Um as the you
wouldn't know it today from the weather,
but as the weather gets nicer and people
are wanting to do camping, um we wanted
people to know what uh kind of a playing
field they were going to have come fall.
And I would stand for any questions. Mr.
Chair,
>> Councilman White.
>> Thank you, sir. Through you, uh, Dr.
Aldridge, um, I appreciate trying to,
uh,
clarify some of these things u before
the time frame ensues. Um my question is
and and we were sitting next to one
another when all of the when we had all
the discussion on this original
ordinance. There was a great deal of
work that we all did to come to a
compromise
uh in order to uh reach a solution that
that for the most part everybody agreed
on. Do in your opinion, do these changes
do anything to upend all the work that
we did in order to come up with that
compromise?
>> Yeah, I think that's a great question,
Councilman White. Um, I think that the
compromise, uh, which the permits was
one of those compromises, right? Um, and
that was to allow people time, uh, to
buy a permit for three days. it would
allow them to load or unload their motor
home or their oversized vehicle um for
things like hunting. It was never the
permits were never meant to
basically be a loophole so that they
wouldn't have to um make other
arrangements. So I I think that um the
compromise that was made which allowed
the permits for the packing and
unpacking um or loading and unloading in
the um season where these aren't allowed
on the street um is still intact. I
think that what we've seen is
unfortunately an abuse of that and so
that's um something we're trying to
remedy and in talking with Chief
Francisco and Captain James may be able
to address this as well. um he really
didn't feel like he could limit it um
himself um when an individual came
forward to buy those permits without
guidance and direction um in ordinance
from the council.
>> Thank you. No other questions.
>> Okay. Any further public comment in the
room?
>> Mr. Chairman,
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Excuse me. Um thank you, Mr. Chairman.
Through you, Dr. Aldridge. Don't run
away, please.
Uh, and I I I have a similar concern to
Councilman White. Um, I wasn't on the
council obviously when all this was
done, but I remember following the
debates uh with a great deal of
interest. Um, and I guess what I'm
worried about is whether we're going to
have a room full of people back here
next Monday as we go through this. Um,
and um, so and perhaps Captain James can
can help. I I I just want to make sure
that if we're going to tinker with this
ordinance that we do all the things that
are necessary for it and not just kind
of peacemeal through it. Um and um from
what I understand when this was first
adopted it was done kind of the last
minute in December. Lot of discussion
about it. Um and a lot of sort of last
minute compromises. Um, but I mean, can
can you assure us or somebody assure us
that, you know, this is this is actually
going to both fix real problems? Um, and
and second of all, that the police
department is actually, you know,
willing and able to do the kind of
enforcement and uh as we remove the
compliance department uh from that role.
Thank you.
Councilman Wolf through um you Chairman
Esabel, the police department really has
been doing the enforcement on this
already.
Um it's the community service officers
that go out when you refer this um as a
complaint. they are the CSOS are the
ones who go out and um take a look at it
um are doing or and I don't know if
police officers also do this as well but
do the measuring and then also are
giving warnings or tickets um those have
been the responses I've gotten from the
um C csos um and usually there's an
entire list that's sent at a time and
then get a response back of where every
one of those is on that list and what
what was done or what they found to be
true. Um
I can't assure you that there is not
going to be a room full of people. Um
I'm always hopeful that people will
engage and um have their input, but I
don't believe that any of this is
changing um the intent of the um
ordinance that we worked on and that we
um basically crafted with a lot of
public input. Um we have received
several emails and um thank yous from
people in our community over the last
year telling us how um much it it's
improved their quality of life and their
ability and their safety in their
neighborhoods. So um I don't believe
that this is going to be one that
generates a lot of um
uh comment but you never know what
excites people. So um I wouldn't be able
to guarantee that. So, Captain James,
>> welcome. Captain,
>> uh, Mr. Chair, Captain James, Shy Police
Department. Um, yeah, first of all,
thanks for looking at this again and
thank Dr. Aldridge because most of these
issues are enforcement issues and and
the the problems that we're experiencing
with the enforcement. Uh, the first
thing is is the permits. In the original
ordinance, there's zero guidance on what
the chief is to use to either approve or
deny a permit. It just says they will
then get a permit. Um, so this this
narrows that down and actually gives the
T the chief something to draw on when he
says no. Um, we're going to have to
figure out how to track that because
that'll be, you know, we just get the
permit request. So, how do we know if
they've put in for more than two in the
last 30-day period? So, that's that's
something we're going to have to work
through with the with the clerk's
office. Um, and we have such a good
relationship with them. I'm I'm sure
we'll figure out some way to track that.
Um, the the the tire thing is is great
and that that will help on enforcement.
I can tell you that one of the biggest
complaints we get is someone will will
make a complaint, our CSOS will go
measure and they'll go, "Well, it's
clearly taller than that." Well, we
struggle with the air conditioner units
on the top of these. We we're not going
to put our cso on on the top of these
climbing on other people's property to
measure up there. And so I don't know if
some some brainstorming for for
additional guidance on that, you know,
maybe rather than 9 foot or 8 foot six
with roof attachments, you know,
something to that so that it just makes
it more or 8 foot. I know my air
conditioner on my fifth wheels just
about 12 in. And so something to that
effect where you can look, you can see a
roof attachment or just say air
conditioner because they're used it's
almost always an air conditioner um that
that adds that extra height. But when
it's in the middle, it's it's really
impossible to measure. Um especially
considering that our our lone cso at
this time is probably 5'4. Um doing any
any measuring up is is very difficult
for her at that point. So um but yeah,
this clarity really helps us going
forward in enforcing this.
>> Any other questions for the captain?
Any other public comment in the room?
Any public comment online?
Public comment online.
Closing public comment. Come back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chair, I move to adopt uh I move to
approve on second reading.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved by Councilman White,
second by Councilman Wolf. Any further
discussion,
>> Mr. Chairman?
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you.
Um,
I I was torn about this uh because I
really don't, as much as I love seeing a
room full of people, really don't want
to have another repeat of what uh all of
you went through before. Um, but it
sounds like this is a limited and and uh
an improvement to the existing
ordinance. And I do agree with you, Dr.
for Aldridge. Um that um this has
improved it's improved my neighborhood.
There used to be a giant one right at
the end of my street. Uh and um and it's
gone now. Um that's been significant.
And so um based on that and your
discussion and captain, thank you very
much for your comments. Um I'll um I
will vote I on this.
>> Any further comments before we vote?
>> All in favor signify by saying I. I
>> any opposed?
>> No.
>> Recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to approve. Next item
>> number 23 resolution reappropriating the
fiscal year 2026 budget of the city of
Cheyenne in accordance with the
provisions of Wyoming state statute
16-4-112
and 16-4-113.
>> Staff report.
>> Hello Mr. Chairman, members of the
committee, my name is Robin Lochman for
the record and I'm the city treasurer.
Before you today is the third
reappropriation for the fiscal year 2026
budget. I've outlined the details in the
attached memorandum, but I will walk
through the key items for your
information. First, within the general
fund, we are requesting a total of
$118,336
from reserves.
This encompasses $18,336
for seed click fix and granicus software
subscriptions. These costs were
previously covered by ARPA funds which
are no longer available. And we also are
requesting $100,000 for the modification
to contract 8267
to support design services for the
renovation of the former Larmy County
Senior Activity Center and the municipal
court second floor which was previously
both approved by the governing body.
Next, we are requesting new grant funds,
including $2,514,599
for the High Plains Arboretum
renovation, construction, demolition,
and abatement projects, previously
approved by the governing body,
$16,79
for reimbursement by BOPU for the 18th
Street storm sewer interceptor project,
$5,500
for a visit Cheyenne marketing grant,
$5,6 $610 for the Wyoming Office of
Homeland Security for a pass through
funding for the 18th Street storm sewer
interceptor project, $4,000 from US
Marshall Service funding for the
Cheyenne Police Department task force
overtime.
In addition, we are requesting
$125,000
from recreation program fund reserves
for conceptual design of child care
program renovations and expansion, as
well as additional part-time gymnastic
staff.
$100,000 from Belvore Ranch Recreation
Fund Reserves for trail and access
improvements,
$78,442
for CDBG funding that was reallocated
from the Lincoln Park project to the
Optimus Park project.
Next, within the specific purpose option
tax botanic gardens on&m fund reserves,
we are requesting $95,000
for unanticipated repairs and
improvements of the Cheyenne Botanic
Gardens.
Additional smaller adjustments include
$17,542
in the civic center fund for artist
payouts, $17,000 in the perpetual care
fund for interest transfers to the
general fund, and $6,000 combined for a
smaller multiple fund out um that fund
items that were outlined in the memo. In
total, this reappropriation reflects a
net budget increase of $4,596,257
across all funds with only $118,336
coming from general fund reserves.
The appropriate director should be here
to answer any um questions you have and
I'm available as well. Thank you.
>> Any questions from the committee to the
treasurer or any of the directors?
>> One question, Mr. Chair, through you.
Um, Robin, not sure if uh the last item
on the first page, uh, the Can you
explain the funds that were reallocated
from the Lincoln Park project to the
Optimus Park project or if Director
Sanchez is on, could he explain that?
Not quite sure what that pertains to.
>> Um, Mr. Chairman, through you, that was
a a grant, a CDBG grant.
>> Okay.
>> That was given.
>> Um, and then they didn't spend it. So,
>> and I see Jason just back there. He was
coming to the rescue and too quick for
Jason.
>> So, thank you. No further questions, Mr.
Chair.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Chair, for you. Uh,
thank you, Miss Lockman. Where it says
on uh first page, again for the public,
you're following on where it says
memorandum says recreation programs uh
fund reserves 125,000. It says uh con
conceptual design for child pro program
renovations and expansion. Um, what is
that exactly?
>> Mr. Chairman, that would probably be
good for director Sanchez,
>> director.
>> Mr. Chair, through you, Jason Sanchez,
community wrecking events. So, our uh
rec camp and rescue programs are
currently housed at the Pioneer Park
Center. Uh, we have about 290 kids in
our rec camp and we have 60 kids on a
waiting list. Uh the building is was
constructed in the early 1970s and so
we're doing some conceptual plans to to
see what it would cost and what the
capabilities would be to expand that
building. Uh we're in the beginning
stages of that. Um the fund uh pays for
itself. The program pays for itself. So
we're using revenues from that program
to for the design.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> No further questions.
>> Councilman White.
>> Um
no questions.
>> Okay. We'll go to public comment in the
room.
Any public comment in the room?
Public comment online.
Go ahead.
Uh Maj, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Hi, Mandy Shadic. I don't live in this
city, but I'm just curious about um the
funds going for advertising for the um
botanical gardens
and civic center and ice event center
out of state marketing.
As I understand the Botanic Gardens has
its stuff pretty locked down
financially, so I'm just curious. Thank
you.
Who wants to take that question?
>> Madam Treasur,
>> Mr. Chairman, I there's no funds that
are going to advertising. It's going for
renovation at the Cheyenne Botanic
Gardens going
>> Mr. Chair, uh if if the on the second
page, it specifically indicates that the
uh funds for Botanic Gardens were for
building repairs and improvements. And
so that money is coming out of that
special purpose tax fund reserves.
>> Okay. Does that answer your question,
ma'am?
>> Mr. Chairman,
>> um,
>> she's Oh, she's probably referring to
the visit Cheyenne grant.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> For advertising
>> and it's a grant that we she received
from visit Cheyenne.
>> Yeah, that's a grant. Ma'am, do you have
any other questions?
Uh, no thank you. Not at this time.
>> Any further public comment online?
>> Mr. Miller, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
>> Members of the finance committee, for
the record, this is Charles Miller. I'm
stepping in to formally audit the fiscal
logic of the expenditures. The previous
caller just brought into the record
regarding the civic center, the Botanic
Gardens and municipal marketing. You are
currently discussing outofstate
marketing for these venues yet your own
quarterly financial Oh, I'm sorry. Give
me a second here.
>> Oh, point order. Uh, Mr. Chairman,
there's nothing in there in this
reallocation.
Uh would would you guys mind voting on
on that as a as a whole that point of
order?
>> I'll second that.
>> Looks like I got three councilmen all
voting on affirmative on the point of
order.
So stick to the item, Mr. Miller.
>> Um okay. And so I I guess what am I
authorized to speak on right now
specifically?
>> Any of the items that are listed under
the reappropriation?
>> Um okay. So is the botanical gardens uh
one of those items
>> building repairs?
>> Um and then the the the civic center
You have a question about the repairs.
>> Um, well,
uh, the civic center is okay to speak
on. Is that correct?
>> On the artist payouts only.
Um, I guess what I have to say is that
uh it um you can't you can't justify
Oh, I'm sorry.
Sorry. Give me two seconds here. Um you
you can't justify allocating uh tens of
millions of public dollars towards
failing entertainment venues, decorative
tile, and out of state marketing while
capping the lead service line
replacement budget at $500,000.
enough to fix barely 40 pipes and
handling families with to handling
handing families with toxic drinking
water a plastic filtration pitch.
>> Mr. Miller, you're getting off subject
again. And I guess
>> the capital misallocation is
mathematically verifiable.
>> Um, and
>> Mr. Miller, you're being called out of
order again.
>> Okay.
>> The civic center artist doesn't have
anything to do with drinking water.
>> Okay. Um well I will uh pass. Thank you.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any further comment
online
and closing public comment back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chair move to adopt. Second.
>> Second. Moved by Councilman Wife. Second
by Councilman Moody. Any further
comments?
>> Just just one uh point of clarification.
uh the uh caller uh had indicated
millions of dollars when talking about
the civic center and the item clearly
states that that number uh that amount
is $17,542
>> dire council Moody.
>> Thank you Mr. Chair through you. And
then on page one everybody where it says
local and state grant for additional
revenue wasn't talked about. I know
we've talked about this a lot. This is
for the arboritum. Hopefully it could
become a state park one day. This is
very important for tourism in the
future. So, wasn't brought up, but
hopefully we can get off consent
agendas. I think this needs to be
highlighted. This is very important for
our tourism industry. Thank you,
>> Councilman Wolf. Uh, Mr. Chairman, thank
you through you. Um, I just want to make
a point that, um, this is routine
business. This is what has to happen in
a business as in a government as complex
as this. Uh and um we should appreciate
the attention to detail that the
treasurer and her office and all of the
state all of the city agencies bring to
this. Some of these matters we've in
fact already approved and they were this
is just reconciling the books. Um others
are um are a bit different but um I for
one appreciate uh immensely what uh the
treasur is doing and and bringing this
before us um and um uh look forward to
voting to approve it. Thank you.
>> Okay. All those in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I. Seeing that that votes unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
will be to adopt at the next meeting of
the governing body. Next item
>> number 25 resolution appropriating
excess funds from the November 2nd, 2021
1% specific purpose sales and use tax
for the acquisition of real property.
>> Staff free
you. Um Dr. Michelle Aldrich, W 3 city
council. Um, I wanted to I
speak to this um because this w was a
result of the tour that we did of the
Larmy County Senior Center and the
conversation that was had about being
able to use the overages from fifth
penny uh sales tax or I'm sorry, six
penny sales tax um that was done
previously um that we had not expended
all of those funds for um and being able
to utilize those in the purchase of the
um former senior center that will become
part of the uh city annex um in that
building. Um so that's what this um
resolution is to do is to take those
overages that um we don't know the
definite amount yet but we know based on
historical performance um about what
that should be and utilizing those um
overages in order to be able to purchase
that property um for a future
annexation.
>> Questions for Dr. Aldridge from the
committee?
Oh, okay. We'll go to public comment in
the room.
Any public comment in the room?
We'll go to public comment online.
Close public comment. Come back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Uh, Mr. Chairman, I move to adopt.
>> Been moved by Councilman Wolf. Second by
Councilman White. Any further
discussion?
>> Uh, Mr. Chairman.
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Um, thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through
you. I guess this is a question maybe
for the treasurer or perhaps for Dr.
Aldridge or the mayor or the chief of
staff. Um, and I guess my only question,
I mean, I I certainly support this doing
it this way, but I I guess my only
question is, is this the best way? Is
this the way we want to do this? uh
assuming that there are other ways that
in fact uh we could uh we could fund
this real estate transaction.
>> Madam Trader
>> uh Mr. Chairman um it would either need
to be this funding source or general
fund reserves. So it's a policy
decision.
>> Welcome Madam Chief of Staff.
>> Mr. Chairman Amber Ash, chief of staff
um through you. Um so this would be
appropriate would go into reserves
anyhow to be allocated according to the
ballot propos proposition. Um it's a
little more restricted there. So it
makes a lot of sense to do it this way.
>> Thank you.
>> All in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Any opposed?
Seeing that that vote is unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
will be to adopt at the next meeting of
the governing body. Next item
>> number 26 resolution adopting the title
six program for the Cheyenne transit
program for the city of Cheyenne Wyoming
>> staff report.
>> Good morning um chair through you Aaron
Johnson Cheyenne transit program
administrator. Um before you is our
title six transit uh program policy that
we uh update every three years and we
are due for this. Um and this is what we
are bringing to you today
>> and I stand back for questions.
>> You have questions from the committee
for staff.
>> Mr. Chair, I'll just provide some
clarification as a an employee of white
dot. Um all all transit programs in the
state who receive federal transit funds
as this one does are required to
complete this plan uh every 3 years. So
the update is something that's been done
as long as I can remember. Um so just
wanted to provide a little background.
>> I don't work with this program directly
so
>> I don't have to declare a conflict.
>> All right. Thank you. Okay. We'll go to
public comment. in the room.
Any public comment online,
>> Mr. Miller? You can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Um, yes. Th this is for Mr. uh White. I
I was just wondering uh what the uh your
statement that you just made about uh
conflicts. Uh could you uh maybe go into
a little bit of detail about what uh
would uh require you to declare a
conflict versus what wouldn't require
that.
>> Mr. Miller, he said he didn't have a
conflict.
>> I I was just uh um wondering what the
what the uh trigger would be there for
him to have to answer. I believe that
>> Mr. Miller. Uh, let me provide some
clarification to you. I work for the
Wyoming Department of Transportation in
my day job. That's what keeps uh that's
how I pay my mortgage. Um, so uh the
program that oversees federal transit
fundings uh from the United States
Department of Transportation is called
the local government program, which I do
not work with. And so I just wanted to
point out that since I am not an
employee of the local government program
for WOT that I do not need to de declare
a conflict of interest in this matter.
>> Oh yeah. And I and I was just wondering
what what uh would be the uh you know
stipulations cuz I I believe that you
guys had uh moved on on some type of uh
ordinance or or or law that was um uh
you guys did not uh pass a uh a
requirement that that was going to be uh
requiring you guys to to state any
conflicts of interest.
>> Mr. Miller, uh, at the beginning of the
year, we all sign a document that has a
list of everything that we discuss and
it's pretty thorough and then, uh, we
sign and date that that we either have a
conflict with one of those items or if
we don't have a conflict with any of
those items, that's public record.
>> Thank you.
>> Any further public comment online?
In
>> closing public comment, come back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to adopt.
>> Been moved by Councilman Moody, second
by Councilman White. Any further
discussion?
All those in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that, that votes unanimous. The
recommendation of the finance committee
will be to adopt at the next meeting of
the governing body. Next item.
>> Number 27. resolution expressing the
support of the governing body for the
submission of an application by the
Cheyenne Transit Program to the Wyoming
Department of Transportation for grant
funding under the Wyoming rural public
transportation grant.
>> Staff report
you Aaron Johnson Cheyenne Transit
Program Administrator. Um before you is
our uh authorizing resolution for us to
request uh $32,000
and $800 302
$862,000
for a match for our program income for
operations. This is an annual request.
>> Questions from the committee for staff?
Seeing none, we'll go to public comment
in the room.
online.
Public comment online.
>> Seeing none. Closing public comment.
Back to the committee. What's your
pleasure?
>> Mr. Chair, I move to approve. Second.
It's
>> been moved by Councilman White, second
by Councilman Moody. Any further
discussion?
All those in favor signify by saying I.
Seeing that that votes unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
will be to adopt at the next meeting of
the governing body. Next item, number 28
resolution approving the budget of the
Cheyenne Downtown Development Authority
for the fiscal year beginning July 1st,
2026 and ending June 30th of 2027.
>> Staff report.
>> Good afternoon. Sophia Maize, executive
director of the Cheyenne Downtown
Development Authority. For the record,
I'm here to present the DDA's fiscal
year 2027 budget. Um, before I get into
the highlights of this budget, I wanted
to address a correction that is before
you for substitute. Uh there was a
scrivener's error, an administrative
error on the budget that the DDA adopted
on February 23rd this year. Um which
calculated uh the total budget amount to
be $30,000 above what it was actually
approved. Um so there was a
line item 708 event management that the
DDA decided to stripe from the budget.
Um unfortunately that was hidden instead
of deleted. Uh and then it was simply um
in RXL added into the the total line
item or the total budget. Uh so that has
been corrected for your approval. Uh
that means that the total budget is
actually 1,22,800
which is only 196,526
more than the fiscal year 2026 final
budget.
With that correction, I'll run through a
couple of highlights for this year's for
the fiscal year 2027 budget. As I
stated, the total proposed budget is
1,22,800,
uh an increase of approximately $196,500
from fiscal year 2026
final budget. In terms of where the
money comes from, the largest revenue
source is the MI levy assessment
collections, estimated at around $51,610
for this upcoming fiscal year. This
reflects a $14,600
increase from the fiscal year 2026
collections, and we utilized a uh 3% CPI
average annual increase year-over-year.
Uh $434,190
should be drawn uh from the reserves to
fund strategic programs. We also
anticipate a $30,000 grant from the
Cheyenne Larmy County Economic
Development Joint Powers Board, uh,
which is what we have received in the
past or this past year, as well as a
$10,000 Laramie County grant for
economic development. The city is
estimated to contribute about $290,900
to cover payroll, benefits, and
insurance for DDA staff. This is not
included in the DDA's uh operating and
or administrative budget.
The largest part of the budget around
500,000 goes towards our three grant
programs that we have. This includes the
facade impro improvement grant, the
capital improvement grant, and the
sidewalk match program. The facade and
capital improvement grants are allocated
$200,000 each. The uh the facade
improvement is our preservation focus
program um focusing on historic
preservation of facades, but also any
other facade improvements we see
downtown. um the sighting, windows,
things like that of that nature.
The capital improvement grant is our
most utilized program and that can be
used by both property and business
owners or tenants within those
properties for capital improvements such
as signage, benches, and anything in the
right ofway.
The sidewalk match program has been
allocated or has um has been allocated
100,000 for the fiscal year 2027. This
was a pilot program started in 2024 and
uh it is being formalized this year.
We're still working through the
parameters with the city to ensure its
effectiveness. There are some bumps we
need to work through.
The downtown planter program will
receive 87,000. This covers our existing
vendor contract through June 2027 and
and it adds uh the eight water efficient
planters for potentially the southside
corridor or the west edge depending on
how the summer 2026 pilot program goes.
Uh this also includes signage and winter
displays. Sponsorships are budgeted at
75,000. These are allocated on a request
basis throughout the year to events that
are free and open to the public and have
a direct community event.
Community events will will receive
125,000. Um and this is where that error
occurred. The event management prior of
the prior years has been put into this
line item. This is a change from last
year. Uh the DDA is stepping back from
coordinating events directly. Uh this
will cover events that we either
annually support such as uh the Fridays
on the plaza event, the downtown holiday
express shuttle, uh busker program
Cheyenne Day that Visit Cheyenne hosts,
um as well as events that we want to
recruit to downtown such as the Wyoming
Independent Film Festival that we're
working on this summer. We're also pro
proposing a new line item. This is a
$10,000 contribution to Visit Cheyenne's
shop local gift card program that they
are starting to pilot this year. This
would be managed by Visit Cheyenne as
part of the broader shop local
initiative. The board will work with
visit Cheyenne to determine how
participation is accessible to all
downtown businesses if they prefer.
Finally, this budget includes $65,100
$100 in independent office expenses. Uh
the city has provided office space and
all associated support at no cost to the
DDA since March 2023. Um, however, these
expenses are we're the DDA is
anticipating an increase in these
expenses due to the potential of the six
penny municipal building uh renovations,
excuse me. Uh, the board has proactively
budgeted these expenses um in in the
case that an independent office is
needed.
These are new costs uh of operating
outside of the city and they include
rent, utilities, supplies, cleaning,
internet, and renters's insurance. And I
stand for questions. Any questions from
the committee for the director?
Councilman Wolf. Uh
>> thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you. Um
thank you, director Maize. Um
I um in as you anticipate perhaps moving
out of the city space. I mean, have you
bud is there budget in here for moving
costs and all the other miscellaneous
costs that happen when you move?
>> Director Mr. Chair through you. I I
don't believe that there are uh moving
costs anticipated in this budget.
>> Followup,
>> Mr. Chairman. So,
uh
so you're going to get all new furniture
or what do you uh anticipate for that?
And and perhaps that's that's in here.
director,
>> Mr. Chair, through you. Um, I believe
that we did anticipate office equipment
um and new furniture would be a part of
that. I think we anticipated 6,000. I'm
sorry, I'm bringing up my my budget at
the moment.
It's having a slow Tuesday just like me.
Okay, here we go.
Office supplies. This is one. I
apologize. Uh, line item 550, office
supplies. The DVA board budgeted $20,000
and that would include office equipment
and furniture.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Mr.
>> Any further questions from the committee
for the director?
>> Okay, we'll go to public comment in the
room.
Mr. Chair uh and members of the
committee, Wendy Vulk, vice chair of the
downtown development authority. We
appreciate your support and I'm very
encouraged by the hard work and the
dedication that our executive director
has led for our downtown development and
I'm um be happy to stand for any
questions as a member of the board.
>> Any questions for the committee for Miss
Fel?
Thank you for support.
>> Any uh other public comment in the room?
Anyone we go to public comment online?
Public comment online.
Close public comment. Come back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chair, I move to adopt
and I need a second on the adoption.
>> Second.
>> And then, Mr. Chair, I move to amend by
substitute dated May 5th, 2026, which
decreases the total budget by $30,000,
making the total budget amount 1 million
$22,800.
>> Second.
>> Been moved by Councilman White, seconded
by Councilman Wolf. Uh any further
questions on the substitute
comments?
Public comment on substitute
either in the room or online.
None on the substitute. All in favor
signify by saying I.
That's been adopted. Back on the main
motion.
All in favor signify by saying I. I.
>> Any opposed? No.
Okay. The motion
to uh adopt by the finance committee to
the governing body at their next meeting
with Councilman Moody. Voting no. Next
item, please.
>> Number 29F, contract between the city of
Cheyenne and BNSF Railway for a BNSF
railway and grant application 22905
agreement for the Reed Avenue rail
crossing elimination project.
staff report.
>> Good afternoon, Chairman Escoel and
members of the finance committee. Tom
Cobb, city engineer. And yes, I did
change my face. Yes.
>> Just going to say I didn't even
recognize you.
>> Um, in close for your review and
consideration is the 22905 agreement
between the city of Cheyenne and BNSF.
As that I've stated in a few comments
before, um the city of Cheyenne, we're
trying to advance our Reed Avenue
corridor rail crossing elimination
project. And as a part of that federal
administration railroad crossing
elimination program grant, we are
required by federal statute to enter
into a formal agreement with the BNSF
railway. Um as the cost of this is
undetermined yet, but I've had some
discussion with the consultant. This is
this is that the parameter that we were
kind of stuck on for a while. What we've
come up to now is based on conversations
with the railroad and our consultant
that this will approximately be 10% of
the assessed value or the appraised
value of the area that we're using
within the corridor. We are advancing a
an appraisal process, but there is no
money exchange with this agreement. As
I've stated before, this will be part of
the construction and maintenance
agreement in the future. But in order to
move this grant forward, we have to get
this signed with the 22905 agreement. It
simply mentions that we're going to
compensate the railroad at a later date.
So my recommendation for you is I
respectfully request approval of this
agreement in order to advance the
project because again the federal rail
authority will not let administration
will not allow us to move forward with
the elimination project without the
22905 executed. And with that I'll stand
with any questions that you might have
for me.
>> Any questions for the committee for
engineer cop?
>> No. Okay. We'll go to public comment in
the room.
Public comment in the room.
Seeing none, go to public comment
online.
Public comment online.
No. Seeing none, we'll close public
comment. Come back to the committee.
What's your pleasure,
>> Mr. Chair? I move to approve. Second.
>> Been moved by Councilman Light. Second
by Councilman Wolf. Any further comments
or questions?
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you.
Um, just a little concern. There's no
actual numbers like 5 million, 10
million. That's why I'll be a no vote.
Thank you.
>> Okay. All those in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> No.
Recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to approve with council
Moody voting no. Next item
>> number 30D contract modification number
one to contract number 8218 between the
city of Cheyenne and AVI engineering PC
for on call engineering services
>> chairman Escoll um and members of the
finance committee. Tom Cop, city
engineer. Um, this is a continuation of
a contract that did not go in front of
you because it was under the 75,000
limit. Um, what I use this contract for
is given the fact that I do not have a
deputy. Um, Mr. Dehoff supports me to be
able to do some of our projects and
manage things that I can't do. Um, so
it's an extension of myself. Um, we've
worked together for over 30 years and
uh, I have a lot of confidence that he
helps me in many different aspects. So I
would ask for your approval of this
contract modification in the amount of
25,000.
>> Any questions from the committee?
Councilman White.
>> Mr. Chair, through you uh to engineer
Cobb. Um is the deputy position been
posted and will you be conducting
interviews? Any timeline that you can
give us?
>> Chairman through you to Councilman
White, sir. So I've tried different
avenues with this. I I tried it before
and now I've gone a different way. So, I
actually I uh I was looking at positions
that were lower and I still haven't
received the candidates that I want. So,
to answer your question, I'm going to
try to do this again. Um I'm hopeful,
but right now the market is just not
been able to be I haven't found the
right candidate for that position.
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Um thank you, Mr. Chairman, through you.
Um and um thank you, Mr. Cobb. um
particularly for all your work on all
these projects that that we've talked to
you about, but Reed Avenue one. So my my
question is this um is this enough is
this enough money to get you the
critical help that you need.
>> Engineer cop
>> chairman for you to councilman Wolf. So
this will get me to the end of the
fiscal year. I'm going to come back
again to you for something else, but I
wanted to finish out this fiscal year
for now just to clean up the books and
move it forward. So, the answer is not
quite enough, but I'll come back to you
again.
>> Thank you, Councilman Moody.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Cobb. Uh,
could you just uh tell the public how
important this is, especially if there
needs to be some done emergency?
>> Um, chairman through you to to
Councilman Moody, sir. Yeah, it's
extremely important, sir. We I there
it's not only it's it's it's it's
managing projects. It's it's emergencies
that we do have. It's extremely
important. Um there are multiple matters
that occur every day. I have 151 active
contracts right now. Um and
approximately $30 million worth of work.
>> Yep.
Okay. We'll go to the comment
in the room.
Public comment in the room.
Go to public comment online.
Public comment online. Okay, we'll close
public comment and come back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to approve an
amount of $25,000.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved by Councilman Moody,
seconded by Councilman White. Any
further discussion?
>> Just real quick.
>> Council Moody.
>> Thank you. So again to the public, you
know, this was also helpful for
emergencies. You know, god forbid a
bridge goes out or something. God forbid
there's a major pothole, we need this.
Thank you.
>> Any further comments? All in favor
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that that vote is unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
will be to approve at the next meeting
of the governing body. Next item,
>> number 31F, consideration of bid number
S-9-26
for a contract between the city of
Cheyenne and Ryman Corp for the Story
Boulevard extension extension
construction project.
>> Staff report,
Mr. Mayor.
>> Mr. Chairman, members of the committee,
for the record, I'm Mayor Patrick
Collins. Before you and for your
consideration is a contract with Ryman
Corporation to extend Story Boulevard
east to Whitney Road. The bid amount is
not to exceed 3,493,630
and a Scott Royal 85.
This is a really important extension for
the people living in the east part of
our community and it's designed to take
the pressure off an already very busy
Del Range Boulevard. It's going to come
become much more important next summer
when the city closes Del Range Boulevard
from College Drive to Van Beern to widen
and improve Del Range through that road
section. And the new extension will help
take that diverted traffic. It was
originally planned to be built for
reconstruction um of the intersection of
uh Del Range and Whitney that was going
to be started by WOT later this year.
But unfortunately, the county didn't
approve the original design because it
had curbon gutter. That curbon gutter
was there due to a high-pressure gas
line that was permitted in the county
section and buried at a depth that would
not allow for the traditional ditch
along the side of the road. So, we had
to go back and redesign the road by
lifting up the road to allow the county
designed dradage ditch. I'm here to
present because the level of county
participation is has been in question.
As a project was being designed, we
received a letter from the county
commissioners agreeing to pay for
$727,986.60,
which would have been the cost to build
that as a county gravel road for their
section of the road. That was before we
received bids or had a good handle on
what the actual cost of the road
extension would be. The traffic study
came back saying that on day one and
without any detour traffic, this road
would hold about 3,500 cars a day and
that would exceed the county standard
for a a gravel road. And then we
received a second letter agreeing to
increase that participation to $936,6067
and they would pay for half of the cost
to pave the county section of the
project. And um what I understand is
they would pay for a two-inch lift of
asphalt. And I'm assuming they would
hope that the city would pay for the
remaining um and I don't know that the
twoinch lift would have held up to the
amount of traffic that was on that road.
But we finally received the bids and
engineer Cobb was able to speak with a
member of the county commission
directly. And after that conversation,
we received a third letter uh agreeing
to pay $1,161,510.60.
And that was their final position on
their participation on this road. That
reflects a $34,393
shortfall on the bid cost to build the
county's portion of the road. The
calculated portion for the county is
$1,465,930.82.
Now, the county has identified a couple
components that they don't think they
should have to pay for. Now, when you go
to College Drive on the western edge of
the project, it's much higher than
Summit Drive. And uh the steep angle is
not appropriate for an intersection of
this kind, especially with the numbers
of traffic that's going to be going
through it and the speeds. The design
includes building up the approach,
reducing the angle to a safe percentage.
That work would require a retaining
wall, and the county commission has said
they don't want to pay for that in the
amount of $124,920.
The design also has some curbing to
direct the uh storm water flow off
College Drive in the amount of $57,49.
And also the approach to college drive
needs to be m made out of a material to
ask for good friction for acceleration
onto college drive and for the cars
turning onto summit drive. The design
calls for a small section of concrete to
make sure those call the vehicles can
safely make that transition and that
cost us $43,400.
Those are the major parts of that
$300,000.
And so here we are today and I think we
have three choices. Um we could just not
build this project. That's an option for
us. We could reject bids. We could do
the project and accept the county's
offer of the, $1161,000
um and have the Cheyenne taxpayers pay
the additional $34,930.85.
Thank you, Scott. Or we could build the
city's portion of the road and let the
county decide to do what to do with
their portion of it. From my
perspective, the money's been budgeted
and it will never be cheaper to build
the extension than it is today. And so,
um, I guess, Mr. uh chairman Mr. Cobb is
here. Uh he can show you the section of
the road and uh some of the things we
were just speaking about, but we do have
a quandry before us and and what what
should we do, what should we pay for and
um so I wanted to come and explain the
the challenge before us today and look
for your guidance and how we should uh
move forward and I'm happy to answer any
questions or we can wait till Mr. Cobb
is finished and then uh we can determine
how to move forward from there.
Okay, committee. You have any questions
for either the engineer cob or the
mayor.
We did a little quick PowerPoint.
I have a quick question then. So, do you
have an idea of how many feet exactly
the county's portion would remain
gravel?
A quarter mile or
chairman. It's approximately a mile each
there roughly. I'll show you in a map
here in a second just off the top of my
head.
>> There you go. If you could just advance
to the second one, please
chairman Tom City Engineer. Just so you
can see what I've identified here is the
blue portion to the left of the screen
is that we we basically broke this into
geographical means. So, if you recall um
about 3 and a half four years ago now um
I came in front of some of you that are
here now um and we purchased the
property on the the the right side of
the screen from the Whitney Geel family
for approximately $516,000.
The purpose of that was to make this
connection. It's, as the mayor has
indicated, I've said this for a long
time, this is a vital connection to
support emergency services and to be
able to let those folks in those rural
areas be able to move from from east to
west. The only two avenues they have on
the northeast corner are moving up to
Iron Mountain or Del Range Boulevard.
And so those two corridors, most folks
go to Del Range, which is part of our
issue right now that I've got a lot of
constraints and a lot of volume on that
road. So, this connection will help
alleviate that in the future. And as the
mayor indicated, um, both construction
projects would benefit from this being a
detour route. We do expect, you know,
that like the mayor had indicated, over
3,000 cars a day to immediately hit
this. The minute we make the connection,
it goes from 84 cars a day on what would
be the blue section of the county
section of this to to to that 3,000
mark.
And then I did have the no do a model
for blocking or for for both
construction projects. We modeled it by
assuming Del Range and College closed
and Del Range and Van Beern were closed
and at various locations that the amount
of traffic goes up to 5,200 cars a day
on something that used to see 84 cars.
Um, so roughly you can see it's a little
less than a mile in the county section
or just right at and we're we're at more
at the mile. So just under a mile for
the county, a little a mile for ours.
Does that answer your question, sir? Um,
just to show you the next slide, please.
Jennifer, I did kind of indicate this is
what I got from Commissioner Malm
yesterday on the items that the mayor
indicated were removed. They were
highlighted in red and they don't quite
line up. The their printing that they
furnished back to me, I didn't couldn't
line it up perfectly, but it gives you
an idea. It's storm sewer, curbon
gutter, um some surfacing that are in
that western section. Could you go to
the next slide, please?
Now, showing you on the second page,
same thing. And then the third slide.
So, I tried to highlight those areas.
This is the far west side in the plan
set. Um, this is the curb and gutter and
the the concrete fillets that are at the
very edge as tying into College Drive.
And as the mayor indicated, we we did
have to to to raise this up in order to
make it a much smoother transition and
allows something to be a a lot more
stable for when we have traffic that
enters into College Drive. And again,
we're going from 84 cars a day to 3,000
cars a day the minute we open it up. Um
that retaining wall had to be placed.
It's in highlighted in red on the on the
bottom of the page. It it goes along the
property which we refer to as the stone
property. Um we we we there was no other
way to do it. U Mr. Stone did not want
fill on his property. So the only way to
do it was to the retaining wall in
indicated you can't not do the fill
because we need to slopes are around 8
to 13% depending on where you're at. and
then we got it down to about uh 5.5.
Um the the storm sewer is highlighted in
the clouded version. It runs across.
There's a single inlet that dumps into
the ditch on the north north end side.
And then the two driveways um the county
also did not want to pay for the paved
approaches off the roadway both north
and south. And the driveway had to be
done on the south side because again
we're lifting the road up. So, it's
completely modifying the approach into
their house. Um, next slide, please.
This is an extension down the curb and
gutter continues down both sides until
you get through that area, the retaining
wall. And you can see on the north it
goes directly into the ditch. In the
south, they carried it a little bit
further to the the next approach. And if
you have any other questions, me, I'd be
happy to answer.
Any further questions from the committee
to engineer Cobb? Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chairman through you.
Um
uh Director Cobb or the mayor. So this
amount that you're asking us to approve,
how does it resolve the policy question,
Mr. Mayor, that that you just posed to
us?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> I think what I'm looking for is some
direction from the governing body before
you today is a contract uh for the full
project. And uh depending on the
direction that you give us, if you say
that we should go ahead and pay for um
all of the project above the million
dollars that the county is willing to
pay, um then that's what we'll do. um if
you feel like they should pay 100% of
their part of it, um we'll we'll make
that clear to them. And if they don't,
then what do we do? Do we build just our
half of it or do we not do the project?
Uh so I'm I guess I'm looking for
direction from the governing body as to
how you would like to proceed.
>> Mr. Mayor, to to me it looks like that
based on engineer Cobb's numbers that it
benefits county residents by far more
than it does city residents.
>> Mr. Chairman, um you know, that might be
the case today, but someday we're going
to build out that um the Whitney Ranch
area and there will be uh at the corner
of um up there a large number of houses.
So, I can see longterm into the future
we'll have some uh a significant number
of city residents. But today, I agree.
Councilman Wolf,
>> Mr. Chairman, thank you through you. Um,
you know, we we the four of us don't
generally deal with the county on on
these kinds of issues. Um, we we rely on
you and and your expert staff to to have
those discussions and and Mr. Cobb with
his counterpart. And um I guess my
feeling is this project needs to be get
done needs to get done all at once. Um
and
um I I I guess it it depends on your
evaluation, Mr. Mayor, on whether you
think the county's position is
absolutely firm at this point or whether
you know they are uh would be willing to
take another look at it.
>> Mr. chairman through you to Mr. Wolf. Um
I think they've given us their final
offer. Um they've been pretty clear
about that through this whole process
and um I think that 1,161,000
or whatever that number 1,161,51060
they said that's their final position on
this participation. I take them at their
word for that. So, if we are going to do
the full project, um it's going to be up
to this governing body to fund the
difference or we could reject the bids
and not do it or we could build our half
of it and let the county decide how they
want to move forward in the future. We
have a design they could use um when
they get whenever they determine it's
appropriate to do that.
>> Councilman Wolf, you got a followup?
>> I do, Mr. Chairman. Thank you. Through
you. Um,
so the additional funds that the county
should pay but has told us they won't
are funds that we have to come up from
fund through our reserves.
>> Mr. Chairman, through they would come um
we have fifth penny sales tax money and
six penny sales tax money directed
towards our um our road projects. It
would reduce those by that amount. So
$34,000
of city roads would not get repaired. um
as we put them into this project.
>> My opinion is um I don't think we can't
we cannot
do this project.
Now whether that means the city builds
our part and and uh lets the county
decide what they want to do,
I don't know.
Um, but we have to move forward in some
capacity. We can't just reject all bids
and call it good. Too much work's been
done. Um, we all drive Del Range. We
know um the amount of traffic that's on
there per day. The fact that we would
have uh another uh roadway to alleviate
some of that um is very enticing to me
at least. And
um I'm going to move to accept the bid
today in the amount that's listed and
then um if the full governing body wants
to make revisions at the next meeting um
we can do that then. But I but I do
think the project needs to move forward
in some fashion.
Councilman Wolf u Mr. chairman through
you. Um I agree with my colleague from
Oregon one and his thoughtful comments.
Um I think the public would want us to
do this all at once. Uh I'm troubled by
the county's position, but that may be
not here here nor there. Um is this work
that will be done this summer, Mr. Mayor
or Mr. Cob?
Chairman through you to Councilman Wolf.
Um we don't have a schedule yet because
we don't have a contract with Ryman in
place but all for all intents and
purposes yes we have a completion date
that would be work would begin this
summer and hopefully be completed. Sir
>> Councilman Moody uh thank you Mr.
Chairman three. I agree both my
colleagues from W one. I mean, roads,
all of our constituents want, you know,
better roads and more roads to beate the
traffic, but I do think we need to maybe
try to come back to the county, make a
difference, but if we can't, then we do
have a way to fund it. Thank you.
>> I'm in agreement as well. This doesn't
make sense to do half a road and then uh
pardon the pun, but down the road it
probably cost us more to to redo it
later. So,
uh we'll look at it as maybe a savings
and uh we'll deal with the county maybe
on another project down the road
somewhere where we
Yeah. All right. We'll go to public
comment.
any public comment in the room.
>> Uh Wendy Vulk, do you need my address to
now?
>> No. Yes. No. Wendy Vulk. Um citizen of
Ward One, but just want to say I am
supportive of this as a real estate
agent. Um there have been times when
I've needed to get and I think with the
expansion when you're going east west um
on four mile road or on story boulevard
um there are bottlenecks and I do think
with that Whitney Ranch and seeing the
magnitude of how many homes I don't
remember what the final headcount of the
total rooftops I should say that will be
in Whitney Ranch but this will behoove
all of Cheyenne for emergency services
parents school bus drivers getting to
and from um point A to be because there
can be quite a bit of congestion right
at Dell Range and College. So, I'm would
support this. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Any further public comment in the room?
>> Okay, let's go to public comment online.
>> Um, Commissioners Mal and Thompson, you
guys should be able to unmute.
>> Welcome, commissioners.
>> Hey, good afternoon, uh, Mr. Chairman.
Uh thank you for your time here today.
Um I'd like to offer a little bit of
historical perspective from from our
vantage point. So back four to five
years ago when this project was being
discussed um I had a conversation um
with city staff and we agreed at the
time yes absolutely the county should
get that road up to county standards so
that it can be um used for this project.
And at that time the numbers that the
county put together was $700 and some
thousands. The mayor um graciously gave
you those numbers. So we agreed to that.
Um and then we don't hear anything for a
year, two years, three years and then
all of a sudden there's movement on this
and the city comes back and says, you
know, your portion is going to have to
be 930,000.
Um and we say, well, why? Well, there's
some changes that we didn't know about
this gas pipe. and we said, "Okay, we
understand that now that we're getting
close." So, we agreed to that $930,000,
what whatever the number was that the
mayor provided. And then we agree to
that. And then we wait and nothing gets
done and nothing gets done. And nothing
gets done. And then the city comes back
and says, "Well, your portion is going
to be $1.6 million." Um, and at that
point, the county commission said, you
know, we don't have unlimited funds. we
are responsible to the to the taxpayers
and by not doing this project when we
agreed to do it four to five years ago
and the escalating costs that come with
that um we don't think should be our
responsibility. I I think there's also
this fundamental conversation about
should the county have to build a road
to city standards. And when we talked
about that, we said no, that does not
make sense because we don't necessarily
agree with building a road to city
standards when it's in the county. And
so when we took the latest numbers that
came from Mr. Cobb uh earlier this week,
um it was $1.4 million. We said, "Okay,
if we're going to build this road only
to county standards, um, this is what we
would do because we feel that's what we
are responsible for." So, when we took
out the retaining wall, the retaining
wall has to be there because of an
agreement the city has with one of those
land owners because of the project that
they did at Thomas Heights. The county
has nothing to do with that. So, so when
we look at these things that make this a
city type road and not a county type
road, we don't feel that the county
commission should have to to to agree to
those amounts. So again, for the third
time, we are saying, okay, we will
increase our amount for this project. We
fully believe in this project. We
understand this project needs to be
done. Um but but we're going to agree
again when it would have cost us
$500,000 less to do it five years ago.
We're going to go ahead and agree again
to hope so that hopefully you guys can
get this done. There's one other thing I
would like to point out. Um I think Mr.
Cobb mentioned there's 84 trips on this
road per day. Um that's a county road.
Because of the city's development
action, they are going to put 5,000 um
cars. I heard two different numbers,
3,500 and then I heard 5200. But they're
going to put 5,000 cars on that road
anytime we have a development action in
Laramie County. We require the developer
to to upgrade the roads to the standard
that we would require. So you're right,
the road would need to be paved, but we
would require the developer to do that.
Um, again, this is a different
situation. We're partners in this. We're
partners with the city. We understand
the benefit of this road being built.
So, we're saying yes, let us do our
part. And and so that is where our
number comes from. So, with that, um I'm
actually in the room with all five of
the commissioners. Um we would certainly
stand for any questions.
>> Okay. Thank you, Commissioner Thompson.
Uh any questions for any of the
commissioners from members of the
committee?
Not seeing none. They all seem like
they're supportive. So,
>> sounds good. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
Now we'll go to uh none of the other
commissioners want to comment.
Members
of the committee for the record. Uh
Charles Miller, can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Um Commissioner Mal has just exposed the
double standard of this administration's
fiscal policy.
>> Commissioner Miller, that was not
Commissioner Mom that was speaking. That
was Commissioner Thompson.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. That's what it had said
on the um the screen there. Sorry about
that. Um
uh you're proposing to use public tax
dollars to fund a 6,000%
increase in traffic from 84 cars to
5,000 cars. Is that correct?
>> I guess you could look at it that way.
And that's exclusively to support the
private Whitney Ranch development.
>> Not exclusively. No.
>> Um the Well, the county has a policy
that developers pay for the
infrastructure that they necessitate.
Um this city, however, is practicing
developer welfare. You are asking the
public to pay for road upgrades that
private developers should be funding
while simultaneously admitting that your
5-year delay on this project has already
cost us an extra $500,000. Is that
correct?
>> Not entirely.
>> Um well, I'm I'm logging a formal
inquiry. Why is the fiduciary priority
of this committee to subsidize private
real estate growth and pay for 32% cost
overruns caused by engineering
negligence while the $und00 million lead
pipe crisis is treated as an unfunded
secondary?
>> Going back to a water issue that doesn't
have anything to do with this road
issue.
>> Would you guys uh vote on that point of
order?
>> It's all unanimous.
Okay. Thank you.
>> We don't have to vote on a point of
order, sir. As chairman, all it has to
do is be uh moved and then seconded and
then the chair would decide either point
of order taken or point of order not
taken. Point of order does not have to
be voted on.
>> Thank you.
>> Anything further, Mr. Miller?
>> No.
>> Thank you. Any further comment on light?
Further comment on light. Okay. Closing
public comment. Come back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to accept the bid
in the amount of 3,493,630.85.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved by Councilman Moody,
second by Councilman Wolf. Any further
discussion?
>> Real quick, Mr. Chair.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Chairman. through you
and also for the public to know we are
required by Wyoming law to make sure we
have good infrastructure and safety.
This is about as basic as it gets. So,
we do need to improve the road. So,
that's why it'll be an I vote and if we
do have to increase that $300,000,
I say we do it because again public will
be happy that they have better roads.
Thank you.
and and my comment is that in a lot of
cases developers and companies that we
do business with in Cheyenne do help pay
for some infrastructure here.
Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh Mr. Chairman, thank you through you.
Mr. Cobb, um this is um just a question
about the contractor. I I know that uh
Ryman Corporation is in the process or
has completed uh a division of its uh
functions and um again this contract
will stay with what is the Ryman
Corporation highway part of of their
business. Is that right
for you to council? Yes, sir. It's Ryman
Corp. Yes, sir.
Thank you.
>> Okay.
All in favor signify by saying I
see that that vote is unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to approve. Next item
>> number 31G, consideration of bid number
S-21-26
for a contract between the city of
Cheyenne and Construction Specialist
Inc. for the Cheyenne Transit Facility
interior and exterior renovations and
upgrades project
>> staff report.
>> Good afternoon, Chairman. Aaron Johnson,
Cheyenne Transit Program, um and uh
committee. We are bringing a bid forward
for you for the uh Cheyenne Transit
facility over on 1800 Westland Road. Um
we had four biders respond to our um bid
for this and we have uh chosen um
construction specialists for this.
Uh the total amount for this bid is
2,169,500
>> questions from the committee for staff.
Um Mr. Chairman, Councilman Wolf.
>> Thank you, sir. Through you. Um,
>> thank you, Director. Uh, do we have
experience with this contractor?
>> Uh, chair, through you to Mr. Wolf, we
do. Um, this contractor actually did
some of the minor interior uh demolition
that we had needed to do uh to continue
to move this project forward.
So um they are insured and bonded um per
federal and uh regulations and Mr.
Bartlebort can also answer that chair
through you to Councilman Wolf TJ
Bartlebort purchasing manager uh
construction specialist has done a lot
of work for the city over the years.
Their most recent largescale project was
the completion of the concessions
building at Dunar Park. So they
constructed that as well. So they uh
they we've done a lot of work with them
and the projects have all been
successful. Thank you.
>> Thank you so much. Thank you.
>> Any further questions from the
committee?
No. We'll go to public comment in the
room.
Public comment.
Go to public comment online.
Public comment online.
Seeing none, we'll close public comment.
Come back to the committee. What's your
pleasure?
>> Mr. Mr. Chair, I move to accept the bid
in amount not to exceed $2,169,500.
>> Been moved by Councilman White, second
by Councilman Wolf. All in favor signify
by saying I. I.
>> Seeing that that vote is unanimous. The
recommendation of the finance committee
will be to approve at the next meeting
of the governing body.
Again, happy Cinco de Mayo. That's the
end of our agenda and we are adjourned.